<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An informacion and peticion agaynst the oppressours of the poore commons of thys realme compiled and imprinted for this onely purpose that amongest them that haue to doe in the Parliamente some godlye mynded men, may hereat take occation to speake more in the matter then the authour was able to wryte.</title>
            <author>Crowley, Robert, 1518?-1588.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19660</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6086.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S310</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22256763</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22256763</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25280</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19660)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25280)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1749:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An informacion and peticion agaynst the oppressours of the poore commons of thys realme compiled and imprinted for this onely purpose that amongest them that haue to doe in the Parliamente some godlye mynded men, may hereat take occation to speake more in the matter then the authour was able to wryte.</title>
                  <author>Crowley, Robert, 1518?-1588.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By John Daye, dwellyng in Sepulchres parish at the signe of the Resurrectio[n] a lytle aboue Holbourne Conduite,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: To the most Christia[n] asse[m]ble of the Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Crowley by STC (2nd ed.) and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸ B⁶</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Poor --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wealth --  Moral and ethical aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25280:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An înforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion</hi> and Peticion agaynſt the oppreſſours of the poore Commons of thys Realme, compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and Imprinted for this onely purpoſe that amongeſt them that haue to doe in the Parliamente ſome godlye mynded men, may hereat take occation to ſpeake more in the matter then the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour was able to wryte.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>¶ Eſaye. lviii.</bibl> ☞ When you ſuffre none oppreſſion to be amongeſt you, and leaue of youre idel talke: then ſhal you cal vpon the Lord and he ſhal hear you, you ſhal crie, and he ſhall ſaye, Beholde I am at hande.</q>
            <p>☞ Imprinted at London by Iohn Daye, dwellyng in Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres pariſh at the ſigne of the Reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a lytle aboue Holbourne Conduite.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25280:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25280:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the moſt honorable Lordes of the Par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liament wyth the commons of the ſame: theyr moſte humble and dayly O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratour Robert Crowley, wiſheth the aſſiſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Goddes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirite.</head>
            <p>AMonge the manifolde &amp; moſte weyghtie matters, (moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy counſaylours) to be deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muned of in this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and by the ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiſe, aſſent and conſent therof ſpedili to be redreſſed: I thynke ther is no one thinge more nedfull to be ſpoken of, then the greate oppreſſion of the pore communes, by the poſſeſſioners as wel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergie as of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laitie. No doubt it is nedfull, and ther ought to bee a ſpedy redreſſe of many mattiers of religion: as are theſe. The vſe of the ſacraments and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, the vſurping of tenthes to priuat com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moditie, the ſuperfluouſe, vnlerned, vndiſcret and vicious miniſters of the church, and theyr Superſticious and Idolatrous adminiſtraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Of theſe thynges I ſaye ought ther to be a ſpedy reformacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For they are now moſt lyk haſtely to bringe vppon thys noble realme, the ineuitable vengeaunce of God, if they bee not ſhortly reformed: for as muche as it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the almyghty and lyuinge God, to open vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs thoſe abhominacions, which haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore ben kepe ſecret and hyd from vs.</p>
            <p>Theſe thinges, I ſay, are yet far out of ioynt, and had great nede to be refourmed.</p>
            <p>For notwithſtandyng the Kinges maieſties
<pb facs="tcp:25280:3"/> late viſitation: the ignorant people, who haue longe ben foſtred and brought vp in the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and wrong beleue of theſe thynges, and are yet n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doubte, ſecretely inſtructed by their blinde guydes and by them holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtyl in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: wyll not be perſwaded that theyr forfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſuperſtition was not the true fayth of Chriſte, til ſuch tyme as they haue continuyng among them, ſuch preachers as ſhal be able and wyll, by the manifeſte ſcriptur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s proue vnto them that both they and their fathers were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and knewe not how to worſhyppe God aright, but ſhamfuly ſeduced by the couetiſe of the ſhepherdes and guides: ſought him where he was not, and when they thought they had bene mooſte hyghe in his fauoure by doynge, hym ſuche honoure as they thought moſte ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in hys ſyght: then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted they moſt deteſtable blaſphemie, &amp; were abhominable be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore hym.</p>
            <p>☞ Thys knowledge, I ſay, wyll not be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into the heades of the ignoraunte: ſo longe as theyr ſhepeherdes be but hyrlynges &amp; folow liuynges, for ſuch miniſter not to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>grega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but to theyr owne bealyes. They are not ſhepeherdes, but butchars. They come not to feede, but to be fed. And doubtles (moſt chriſten cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſaylours) I thinke it not poſſible to ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de this great enormitie, otherwyſe then by redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynge the order of choſeynge of the miniſters, vnto the order that was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> primitiue church wherof is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned in the Act,<note place="margin">Actu. 1.</note> of the Apoſtles For ſolong as ydle bealies may come to the by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhope and be ſmered for money, God ſhal ſaye to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his prophet.<note place="margin">Iere. 23.</note> You did te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne but I ſent
<pb facs="tcp:25280:3"/> you not. They ſhalle be called feedars, of feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge them ſelues and not of fedyng the flocke, They ſhal ſtudye to pleaſe men &amp; not to pleaſe God. In fine, they ſhall differ nothynge from the craftes men whiche applye an occupacion to gette theyr lyuinge vppon, and not to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to profite the common weale.</p>
            <p>☞ The craftes man ſueth for the fredom of a Citie, not becauſe he intendeth to be a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer of the Citie: but becauſe he hopeth that he ſhall lyue ſo muche the more welthyly hym ſelfe. And eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for lyke cauſes do our miniſters and are lyke ſtyll to do (ſo longe as they maye bee receyued when they come vncalled) applye them ſelues to prieſting, becauſe they lyke wel the ydlenes of the lyfe.</p>
            <p>☞ I doubt not but the Kynges maieſties vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitters know more of thys matter then I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be able to writ. And by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I doubt not, you ſhal be moued to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune of this mattier at the ful.</p>
            <p>☞ The ſacramentes they ſtyl abuſe, vſeinge them as matters of merchaundyce, and chiefly the moſt worthy memory of our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, for that they ſelle boethe to the quycke and to the deade, to the rych and to the poore. None ſhall receyue it at theyr handes, wythout he wyll paye the ordinarie ſhotte, and ſo are they redy to ſerue euery man. They loke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the monei onely and nothynge vppon the mynde. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be taken to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, they pas not. Thei tel the monei, thei loke for nomore. If they wyll deny this to bee true let them ſaye why, they ſuffer the pore to begge money to paye for theyr houſel, as they call it? Perchaunce they wyll anſwer that the money
<pb facs="tcp:25280:4"/> is not payede for the ſacrament, but for the .iiii offeryng dayes. Then aſke I thys queſtian,</p>
            <p>Why thei appoint not another time to receiue it in, then that tyme whyche is to lyttle to bee occupied in declareynge to the people the right vſe &amp; profyte of the ſacramentes, &amp; to inſtructe them ſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do not receiue it to theyr iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but to theyr confort and quietnes of con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience, for which purpoſe it was firſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? Vndoubtedli (moſt chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> counſailours) they can not deni but that they appoynt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue it then, becauſe they wil be ſure of it.</p>
            <p>Theyr doeynges wyll declare it, thoughe they woulde deny it, for none may receyue the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes vnles he do fyrſte paye, the money. And then, wyth how lyttle reuerence it is miniſtred and receyued: euery thriſten hert ſeeth &amp; lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</p>
            <p>Theſe thinges (I doubt not) are ſo euident and playne vnto you: that it nedeth not to tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you wyth manye wordes concerneinge the abuſes therof. Many godly minded men haue boeth written and preached, &amp; do dayely writte and preach, of and agaynſt thoſe abuſes, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I am certen that you haue iuſte occaſion and can do no leſſe but ſeke a furder redres her of (whyche al chriſten hertes do deſire) in thys preſent parliament.</p>
            <p>But as for the oppreſſion of the pore, which is no leſſe nedful to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muned of and reformed then the other: I feare me wyll bee paſſed ouer with ſilence, or if it bee communed of. I canne ſcarſely truſte that any reformacion canne bee had, vnleſſe God do nowe worke in the hertes of the poſſeſſioners of thys realme, as he dyd
<pb facs="tcp:25280:4"/> in the primitiue church, when the poſſeſſioners were contented and very wyllyng, to ſell theyr poſſeſſions and geue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> price therof to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune to al the faythful beleuers. Take me not here that I ſhoulde go about by theſe wordes to perſwade men to make all thinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune: for if you do you miſtake me. For I take God to wytnes I meane no ſuch thyng. But with all myne hert I woulde wyſh that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were ſuffered to eate, but ſuch as would laboure in theyr vocation and callyng, accordynge to the rule that Paule gaue to the Theſſalonians.<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3</note>
            </p>
            <p>But yet I woulde wyſh that the poſſeſſioners woulde conſyder whoe gaue them theyr poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſions, and howe they ought to beſtowe them. And then (I doubt not) it ſhoulde not nede to haue all thynges made commune.</p>
            <p>☞ For what nedeth it the ſeruauntes of the houſeholde to deſyre to haue theyr mayſters goodes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune, ſo longe as the ſtuarde mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth vnto euery man the thinge that is nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for hym?</p>
            <p>☞ If the poſſeſſioners woulde conſyder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be but ſtuardes, and not Lordes ouer theyr poſſeſſions: thys oppreſſion woulde ſone be redreſſed. But ſo longe as thys perſwaſion ſtyketh in theyr myndes. It is myne owne.</p>
            <p>Whoe ſhal warne me to do wyth myne owne as me ſelfe lyſteth? it ſhall not bee poſſible to haue any redreſſe at all. For if I may do wyth myne owne as me lyſteth: then maye I ſuffer my brother, hys wyfe and hys chyldrene, to lye in the ſtrete, excepte he wyll geue me more rent for myne houſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer he ſhal be able to paye Then may I take his goods for that he oweth
<pb facs="tcp:25280:5"/> me and kepe his body in priſon, tournyng out his wyfe and chyldren to periſhe, if God wyll not moue ſome mans herte to pittie them: and yet kepe my coffers full of goulde and ſyluer.</p>
            <p>☞ If ther were no god, then would I think it leafull for men to vſe their poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as thei liſte Or if God woulde not requitre an acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of vs for the beſtoweynge of them. I woulde not greately gaynſaye thoughe they toke theyr pleaſure of them whylſe they lyued here. But foraſmuch as we haue a God, and he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared vnto vs by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripturs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath made the poſſeſſioners but Stuardes of his ryches and that he wyl holde a ſtreyght accompt with them for the occupiynge and beſtoweynge of them: I thynke no chriſtian ears can abyde to heare that more then Turkyſh opinion.</p>
            <p>☞ The Philoſophers who knewe nothyng of the bonde of frendſhippe which Chriſte our mayſter and redemer lefte amonge vs: affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that among fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des al thinges are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune meaneyng that frendſhippe woulde not ſuffer one frende to holde frome an other, the thinge that he hath neede of. And what ſhal we ſaye? Are we not fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des? Suerly if we be not fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: wee beare the name of Chriſte and bee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led chriſtians in vayne. Yea if wee haue not a more perfecte frendeſhyppe then that whereof the Philoſophers ſpeake: wee are but fayned chriſtians we beare the name onely and are no thynge leſſe in dede: For this is the token that Chriſte gaue whereby wee ſhoulde be knowen to be of him:<note place="margin">Iohn. 13.</note> if we loue one an other as he lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vs. Howe he loued vs, is declared by the wordes of the Apoſtle ſayinge,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.</note> that Chriſte
<pb facs="tcp:25280:5"/> gaue hym ſelfe for vs. Accordynge to thys ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emple ought our frendſhyp to be ſuch, that we wyll not ſpare to ſpende our lyfe for the welth of our brothers. Not to fyght in theyr quarell (for Chriſte bade Peter put vp the ſwerde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his place) but to teach the truth boldly with out any feare of death, and not to ſuffer oure brothers to bee led in erroure thoughe preſente death ſhoulde inſue for ſo doynge.</p>
            <p>Some perchaunce wyll thynke that this fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp is to be vnderſtande onely of the paſtors and ſhepherdes towarde theyr flocke becauſe Chriſt ſayth that a good ſhepherde geueth his lyfe for his ſhepe.<note place="margin">Iohn. 10.</note> Forſoeth if the paſtours or ſhepeherdes onely, were the flocke of Chriſte then myght thys frendeſhyp ryght well be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded of them onely. But for aſmuch as the Laie and priuate perſons, are as wel of the flocke of Chriſte as the other: thys frendeſhyp parteineth vnto them noleſſe then to the other. And thys cauſeth me (moſte worthy counſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours) not to feare the diſpleaſure of men in this behalfe, knoweynge for certentie that the greateſte numbre of thys aſſemble are not free from this oppreſſion that I ſpeak of, and that it is farre vnlyke that a priuate perſone by no meanes worthy to be called to ſuche an aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhoulde be fauourably hearde and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of them whom God hath called to be coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaylours of a realme, and chiefly in a cauſe tax<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng &amp; blameyng the Iudges before whom it is pleaded. I might well coniecte wyth my ſelfe, that I ſhoulde in this poynte be compted a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy body, and one that renneth before he is ſent. But I am redi to ſuffer not onli al ſuch report
<pb facs="tcp:25280:6"/> but euen the verye death alſo (if it ſhall pleaſe the almightie and euerlyueynge God to laye it vpon me) for youre ſakes, moſte worthy coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſailours, and the reſidue, my natural brothers of this noble realme.</p>
            <p>☞ And here I proteſte vnto you all, that the ſame ſpirite that ſent Ionas to the Niniuits, Daniel to the Babilonians, Nathan to Kyng Dauid, Achior vnto Holofernes, Iudith vnto the Prieſtes and Elders of the Iewes, the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete to Ieroboam in Bethel, Iohn the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt vnto Herode, and Chriſt vnto the Iewes-wytneſſeth wyth my conſcience,<note place="margin">Eſai. 58.</note> that I renne not vnſent. For eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame ſpirite that ſayd vnto Eſaye, crye and ceaſe not, declare vnto my people theyr wyckednes: cryeth alſo in my conſcience, bydyng me not ſpare to tell the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſeſſioners of thys realme, that vnleſſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente the oppreſſion wherewyth they vexe the pore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues thorough loue to be brothers of one father &amp; membres of one body wyth them: they ſhal not at the laſte daye enherite wyth them the kingdome of Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eldeſt ſonne of God the father, whych hath by his worde begotten hym many brothers &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritours is hys kingdom Vnleſſe, I ſaye, the poſſeſſioners of thys realme wyl repent the vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>olence don to the poore and nedy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of the ſame, and become as handes, miniſtring vnto euery membre his neceſſaryes: they ſhall at the daye of theyr accompt, be bound hand and fote and caſt into vtter darknes, wher ſhal be wep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, wealyng, and gnaſhyng of teach, that is, dolour and yayne, the greatnes wherof canne not be expreſſed wyth tonge nor thought wyth
<pb facs="tcp:25280:6"/> herte. And thys much more ſayeth the ſpirite. Vnleſſe ye purge your ſelues of thys bloude, &amp; ſtop the mouthes of the pore that the voyce of theyr complaynt come not vnto mine eares: I wyll not proſpere your counſayles in the refor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe abhominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which I ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto you, but wyll leaue you to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of errour, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prince of thys worlde, whoſe dearlin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges ye are ſo longe as ye ſeke not the welth of the nedy, but your owne priuate commoditye. Theſe thynges hath the ſpirite of God ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Heauen and earth ſhal periſhe, but the wordes of the ſpirite ſhall not periſh, but be fulfylled. Nowe herken you poſſeſſioners, and you rich men lifte vp your ears, ye ſtuards of the Lord marke what complayntes are layede agaynſte you in the high courte of the liueynge God.</p>
            <p>Lorde (ſayeth the Porphete) haſt thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vs? doeſt thou hide thy ſelfe in the tyme of our trouble? Whylſe the wicked waxe proude the pore man is aflicted and troubled. Would to God the wicked myght feale the ſame thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that they inuent for other. For the ſinnere prayſeth hym ſelfe in the deſyers of hys ſoule, and he extolleth and fetch furth the couetouſe man. He prouoketh the Lorde and is ſo proud that he wyll not ſeke hym. He neuer thynketh vpon God. His wayes be defiled at all tymes. He loketh not vpon thy iugementes Lorde, be will reuenge hym vpon al hys enimies.</p>
            <p>He thynketh thus with hym ſelfe, I wyll not remoue from one generacion vnto an other without miſchefe. Hys mouth is full of male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and euill reporte, fraude &amp; deceyte:<note place="margin">Eſai. 50.</note> and vnder his tonge is afliction and iniquitye.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25280:7"/>
            <p>He lyeth in wayte wyth the rychemen of the villages or graynges, in ſecrete corners, to the intent to ſlea the innocent. His eyes are fyexed vpon the pore, he layeth awayete, euen as a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in his denne. He layeth a wayte to take the poore man by force, and when he hath gotten him wythin his reache, then wyll he take hym violentlye. In hys net will he ouerthrowe the pore, and through hys ſtrength ſhall the muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the oppreſſed be ouer charged and fall. For in his hert he ſayeth, God hath forgotten God turneth a waye hys face, and wyll neuer regarde the oppreſſion of the poore, etc. to the ende of the ſame Pſalme.</p>
            <p>☞ What ſentence (thinke you) wil the Lorde gyue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this euidence? No doubt (moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy counſellers) euen the ſame that we reade in Eſaie the Prophete I loked for iudgement and rightouſe dealynge amongeſte my people and beholde there is iniquitie,<note place="margin">Eſaie. 5.</note> I loked alſo for iuſtice, and beholde there is an outcrye. Wo be vnto you therefore, that do ioyne houre vnto houſe, &amp; couple one fielde to an other, ſo longe as there is any ground to be had. Thinke you that you ſhal dwel vpon the earth alone? The Lorde of hoſtes ſayeth the prophete hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken theſe wordes vnto me. Manye large and goodlye houſes, ſhall be deſerte, and wythout inhabitauntes .x. acres of vynes ſhal yelde but one quarte of wyne, and .xxx. buſhelles of ſeede ſhall yelde but .iii buſhelles agayne. Beholde you engroſſers of fermes, and teynements be holde I ſay, the terrible threatnynges of God whoſe wrath you can not eſcape. The voyce of the pore (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you haue with money thruſte
<pb facs="tcp:25280:7"/> out of houſe and home, is well accepted in the eares of the Lorde, and hath ſteared vp hys wrath agaynſte you. He threateneth you moſte horrible plages. Ten acres of vynes ſhal yelde but one quarte of wyne, and .xxx. buſhelles of ſede but .iii. buſhelles agayn. The ſede of God<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des worde ſowen in youre hertes, ſhall be bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayne and not bringe forth fruite.</p>
            <p>☞ For couetyſe, the rote of al iuelles, occupi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth that grounde ſo that the heauenlie ſede can bi no meanes geue encreaſe. This is a plage of al plages moſt horryble And doubt ye not you leaſe mongres, that take groundes by leaſe to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntente to lette them out agayne for double and triple, the rent: your parte is in this plage The Lorde ſhall take his ſpirite from you. He ſhall forbyd the cloudes of his mercy, to rayne vpon you wyth the ſwete dwe of hys greace. And you ſurueighers of la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, that of x.li. la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de can make .xx. you ſhall not be forgotten in the effu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of thys plage.</p>
            <p>☞ For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you haue multiplied your re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ttes to the higheſte, ſo that ye haue made all youre tenantes your ſlaues to labour and toyle and bringe to you all that maye be plowed and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out of youre groundes: then ſhal death ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daynly ſtrike you, then ſhall God wythdrawe his confortable greace from you, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall your conſcience prycke you, then ſhall you thynke with de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>perat Cain, that your ſinne is greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it may be forgeuen. For your owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall iudge you worthye no mercye, be, cauſe you haue ſhewed no merci. Yea the ſame enimie that hoth kendled, and doeth yet mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne in you thys miſcheuouſe, outragiouſe
<pb facs="tcp:25280:8"/> and vnſaciable couetouſnes: ſhall then bee as buſy to put you in mynde of the wordes of Chriſt ſaienge, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame meaſure that you haue made vnto other, ſhalbe nowe made vnto you.</p>
            <p>You haue ſhewed no mercye: howe can you than loke for mercye? Oh noble counſailours be mercyful to your ſelues Deſtroye not your owne ſoules to enriche your heyres. Enlarge not your earthly poſſeſſion wyth the loſſe of the eternal enheritaunce. Learne to knowe the eſtate that God hath called you vnto, &amp; to lyue accordinge to your profeſſion, Know that you are al miniſtres in the common weale and that the procion which you are borne vnto, or that your prince geueth you is your eſtate. Knowe that your office is to diſtribute &amp; not to ſcrape to gether on heapes, God hath not ſette you to ſurueye his landes, but to playe the ſtuardes in hys houſeholde of this world, and to ſe that your pore felow ſeruantes lacke not theyr ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries.</p>
            <p>Conſider that you are but miniſters and ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauntes vnder the Lorde oure God, and that you ſhal render a ſtreyght accompt of your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtracion. Stand not to much in your own conceyte, gloriynge in the worthyneſſe of your bloude, for we are all one mans chyldren, and haue (by nature) lyke right to the rycheſſe and treaſures of thys worlde wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rouf oure natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral father Adame was m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de Lord and Kinge. Whiche of you can laye for hym ſelfe any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e whyche ſhoulde poſſeſſe the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of this worlde, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame cauſe maye he founde in hym alſo whome you make your ſlaue? By nature (therefore) you can claime no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thinge
<pb facs="tcp:25280:8"/> but that which you ſhall gette wyth the ſwet of your faces. That you are Lordes and gouernoures therfore, commeth not by nature but by the ordinaunce &amp; appoyntment of God. Knowe then that he hath not called you to the welth and glorie of this worlde: but hath char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged you wyth the greate and rude multitude.</p>
            <p>And if any if them periſhe thorowe your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faute, knowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for certentie, that the bloude of them ſhalbe required at your handes. If the impotent creatures periſhe for lacke of neceſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: you are the murderres,<note place="margin">Ezech. 33</note> for you haue theyr enheritaunce and do not miniſter vnto them.</p>
            <p>If the ſturdye fall to ſtealing, robbyng &amp; reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge: then are you the cauſers therof, for you dygge in, encloſe, and witholde from them the earth out of the which they ſhoulde digge and plowe theyr lyueynge.<note place="margin">Pſal. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> For as the Pſalmiſte writeth. All the heauen is the Lordes: but as for the earth hee hath geuen to the childrene of men.</p>
            <p>☞ The whole earth therfor (by birth ryght) belongeth to the chyldren of men. They are all inheritours thereof indifferently by nature</p>
            <p>But becauſe the ſturry ſhoulde not oppreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the weake and impotent: God hath apoynted you ſtuards to geue meate vnto his houſholde in due reaſone. And if you be founde faythfull in thys litel: then knowe that he wyll preferre you to muche greater thynges. But if ye bee found oppreſſing your felowe ſeruauntes: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowe for certentie, that the Lorde your mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhall at hys comeynge, rewarde you wyth many ſtrypes. Call to your remembraunce the Hiſtory of Kynge Nabuchodonoſor whoe for<note place="margin">Luke. 12. Dani. 4.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:25280:9"/> his preſumption became, as a brute beaſt, fead<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinge vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> graſſe and hey as other beaſtes dyd.</p>
            <p>☞ Conſidre Pharao wyth his great armie, whom the Lorde ouerwhelmed in the red ſea for oppreſſing and perſecuting his people. Yea conſidre al the nobilitie that haue poſſeſſed the earth, euen from the begynnyng: and then ſaye howe you be theyr ſucceſſours, and by what title you cleyme that which was theyrs.</p>
            <p>☞ Many hundred yeres ſence, the noble Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mains helde all Europa, and parte of Affrike and Aſia, in quiete poſſeſſion: and where are they that ſucceade them in theyr impeir?</p>
            <p>The brutiſhe Gothes inuaded and va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the impier of Rome: and where are theyr ſucceſſours?</p>
            <p>☞ What ſhoulde I ſtande in the rehearſall of the great poſſeſſioners that haue hertofore poſſeſſed the earth, whoſe liniall deſcent ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be founde? It ſhal ſuffice me to remitte you to the wordes of the Lorde vnto Nabuchodono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, whiche are wrytten in the boke of Daniell the Prophet.<note place="margin">Dani. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>☞ There ſhal you learne that it is God that gyueth the impier to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it pleaſeth hym, and that all power is from aboue, accordynge to the anſwer that our ſauiour Chriſte made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Pilate, when he bragged hym wyth the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer than he had to crucifie hym and to deliuer hym. Thou ſhouldeſt, ſayed our ſauiour, haue no power ouer me at all,<note place="margin">Iohn. 19.</note> were it not gyuen the from aboue.</p>
            <p>☞ Thus it is euident vnto you (moſte wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy counſaylours) that your power and eſtate cometh frome aboue, and that by nature, you
<pb facs="tcp:25280:9"/> can cleyme nothynge of the poſſeſſions of thys worlde, more then that whiche you gette wyth the ſwet of your faces.</p>
            <p>☞ I doubt not therfor but that your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences do condeſcend and agre vnto that which I haue ſpoken concernynge youre office and miniſterie, knoweynge that God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you to miniſter neceſſaries to the impotent and to defende the innocent.</p>
            <p>☞ Do not therfore neglect thys principalle poynt of your dutie, to ſeke in this parliament a redreſſe of thys great oppreſſion, wherwyth the pore membres of this noble realme, ar moſt vnmercifully vexed on euery ſyde.</p>
            <p>☞ The lande lordes for theyr partes, ſuruey and make the vttermoſt peny of al their grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, byſydes the vnreaſonable fynes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes. And he that wyl not or can not geue all that they demaunde: ſhall not enter be he neuer ſo honeſt or ſtande he neuer ſo greate neede.</p>
            <p>☞ Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a though he haue ben an honeſt, true, faythfull and quiete tenant many yeres: yet at the vacatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his Copie or Iudentur, he muſt paye welmoſte as much as woulde purchayſe ſo much grownde or elſe voide in haſte, though he, his wyfe and childrene, ſhoulde periſhe for lacke of harbour.</p>
            <p>☞ What a ſea of miſchifes hath floued out of thys more then Turkyſhe tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie: what ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte houſholders haue ben made folowers of other not ſo honeſt mens tables: what honeſte matrones haue ben brought to the needy rocke and cardes: what menchyldrene of good hope in the liberall ſciences and other honeſte quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes (wherof this realme hath great lacke) haue
<pb facs="tcp:25280:10"/> ben compelled to fal ſome to handycrafts and ſome to daye labour to ſuſtayne theyr parents decrepet age and miſerable pouertie: what fro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward and ſtoubourne children haue herby ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the yoke of godly chaſtiſement rennyng hedlonge into all kyndes of wickednes and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally garnyſhed galowe trees: what modeſte, chaſt and womanly virgins, haue for lacke of dourie bene compelled either to paſſe ouer the dayes of their youth in vngrate ſeruitude, or els to mary to perpetuall miſerable pouertie: what immodeſte, &amp; wanton gyrles haue hereby bene made ſiſters of the Banke (the ſtumlyng-ſtocke of all fraile youth) and finally, moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable creatures lyinge and dyinge in the ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes full of all plages and penurie: what vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall deſtruction chaunceth to thys noble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme by thys outragious and vnſaciable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the ſurueiers of landes: I reporte me to you (moſte chriſtian counſeilours) whiche are here aſſembled from all partes of thys noble realme, to conſult for the wealth of all the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres of the ſame.</p>
            <p>☞ On the other ſyde, there be certeyne te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes, not able to be lande Lordes, and yet after a ſort they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfaite lande lordes, by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teininge leaſes in and vpon grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and ſo reyſe fines, incomes, &amp; rentes: and by ſuch pillage pike out a portion to main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyne a proude port, and all by pilling and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the poore commons that muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie ſeeke habitations at theyr handes.</p>
            <p>☞ That this is true, I report me to my lorde the Maire &amp; other the heade officers of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of London, who (if they be not ignorant of
<pb facs="tcp:25280:10"/> the ſtate of the Citie) can witnes with me that the moſte parte, yea I thinke ix. of the .x. par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, of the houſes in London, bee ſet and let by them that haue them by leaſe: and not by the owners.</p>
            <p>☞ Howe thei polle the pore tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, would ſone be tryed, if theyr leaſes were conferred w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr rentrolles. It is not to be thought contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry but that the greate leaſmu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers haue greate gains by their leaſes, for the litleons that hold but a piece of houſeing of .xx. or .xxx.s. by yere: can fynde the meanes to holde and dwell vpon the chiefe parte therof rent fre, by letynge out the reſidue for the whole yerely rent.</p>
            <p>☞ I thinke not contrary but theſe thinges do appeare in the ſyght of many to bee but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rey trifles, and not worthy to be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of in ſo noble an aſſemble as this moſt honorable par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. For they are no mattiers concerneyng the welth of the nobilitie, yea it is rather hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to many of them, to haue theſe thynges redreſſed, then any encreaſe of theyr welth.</p>
            <p>Yea euen you (moſte chriſtian counſaylours) whych are here aſſembled, to debate the weigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie mattiers of thys realme: are not all ſo free from this kynde of oppreſſion, but that you coulde be well contented to wyncke at it. And therfor, for aſmuche as the inordinate loue of men towarde them ſelues is ſuch, that eyther they can not ſe theyr owne fauts, or elſe if they do ſe them, or be tolde of them, they take them not to be ſo great as they are in dede: I thinke it no meruayle, though ſuch of you (moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy counſaylours) as haue any profite by this oppreſſion, do wythin them ſelues deride and
<pb facs="tcp:25280:11"/> laugh to ſcorne my fole hardines and raſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe herein, knowyng that it is not the vſe of them that be aſſembled to the intent to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhe ſuche thynges as ſhall be for the wealth of a whole realme: to condeſcende and agree to thoſe thynges whiche ſhall be diſprofitable vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the chiefe membres of the ſame.</p>
            <p>☞ Truth it is (moſte worthy counſaylours) I might well and worthely be laughed at: if I woulde attempt any ſuch thing. But the thing that hytherto I haue ſpoken of: is not to the diſprofite of any, but to the great commoditie and profite of all the whole realme.</p>
            <p>☞ For what diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie is it to the heade, ſhoulders, the armes, and other the vpper me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres of the bodie, beinge already ſufficiently clothed: to put on the legges and feete a peare of hoſe and ſhoes, to defende them alſo from the iniuries of the wether &amp; other hurtes that myght chaunce vnto them in theyr trauaylyng to cary the body from place to place, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moditie and pleaſure? Verely in myne opinion that body is farre vnworty to haue either leg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or feete: that wyl let them go bare, hauyng wherwith to couer them.</p>
            <p>☞ Euen ſo you, beynge the chiefe membres of thys noble realme, and hauing in your han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the wonderful and incomperable riches of the ſame: what ſhoulde it greue you to departe wyth ſome portion thereof, that the inferioure membres thereof, maye at all tymes be able to do theyr miniſterie and office accordyngly.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Once remembre, that as the bodye wyth out the inferioure partes is but lame and as a blocke vnweldy, and muſte, if it wyll remoue
<pb facs="tcp:25280:11"/> from place to place, creepe vpon the handes: euen ſo you, if ye had not the poore membre of this realme to tyll the grounde and do your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther drudgery: no remedy you muſte needes d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it your ſelues.</p>
            <p>☞ Vſe them therfore as the neceſſarie mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres of the miſticall bodye of this moſte noble realme, and be not in thys poynte more vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural then the heathen Philoſophers were.</p>
            <p>They in theyr wrytynges declare no leſſe then I haue wrytten.</p>
            <p>☞ Thys oughte not a lytle to moue you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing chriſtians (whoſe redemer Ieſu Chriſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the ryghte hande of God his father) to ſtudy, not onely to be equal with, but to paſſe the heathen &amp; vnchriſtened in this matter, euen as farre as the excellencie of the name and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion whiche we profeſſe, paſſeth theyrs.</p>
            <p>☞ Remembre (moſt chriſtian counſaylours) that you are not only naturall membres of one body wyth the poore creatures of this realme: but alſo by religion you are membres of the ſame miſticall body of Chriſt, who is the head of vs all (his membres) and eſtemeth all that is done to the leſte of vs his membres, as done to hym ſelfe. For he ſayth.</p>
            <p>☞ What ſo euer ye do to the leſte of theſe litle ones that beleue in me: ye do it vnto me.<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If you therefore, neither wyll your ſelues op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe our ſauiour Chriſte in his membres, nor ſuffre other to do it: fayle not to fynde a redres of this greate oppreſſion, whiche I haue decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the ſame ende. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I doubt not, but God ſhall ſo worke wyth you: that euery man ſhall wyllyngly embrace a reformation of all
<pb facs="tcp:25280:12"/> mattiers of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For the ſpirit of God ſhall dwell in you and in vs all, and Chriſte himſelf (as he hath promiſed) ſhall bee in the myddes a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monge you. Wher as contrariwiſe, if you ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffer our loueinge ſauiour thus to be oppreſſed, he wyll forſake you, he wyll leaue you to the ſpirite of errour. Your reformacions ſhal take no place. All your diuiſes ſhall be abhominable in his ſyght, becauſe ye haue not purged your handes from the bloude of this oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>Let the decres whych were eſtablyſhed in thys place by a parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt aſſembled for a lyke pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: be your preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, not to folow, but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware by them that ye eſtabliſh not the lyke.</p>
            <p>The intent of that aſſemble was noleſſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourm the abuſes of our religion then thys is. But becauſe Chriſte was not deliuered frome oppreſſion: he woulde not be amonge them.</p>
            <p>They were not congregated in hys name, but rather agaynſte hym and hys doctrine, for he hym ſelfe is dear loue, &amp; (as his Apoſtle Iohn writeh) wher this dear loue is not,<note place="margin">1. Epiſt. 4.</note> ther is not he. Thys thynge is well proued by theyr pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceadynges in the ſame Parliament. For they eſtabliſhed articles euen directly agaynſt Gods worde forbedynge to mary, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundynge to put aſunder thoſe that God hath ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether</p>
            <p>☞ If you wyll call theſe articles into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion agayne (as in dede you haue iuſte occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to do) I doubt not but you ſhal be fully per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwaded that they proceaded of the ſpirit of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure and not of the ſpirite of God, becauſe the charitie of God was not amonge them in that aſſemble.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25280:12"/>
            <p>Other thynges therbe wherby the pore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of Chriſte in thys noble realme, are oppreſſed, wherof I haue made no mention, partely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am loth to offende wyth the multitude of my rude wordes, &amp; partely for that I know you can not ſeke for a redres of theſe thynges wherof I haue ſpoken: but the other wil offer them ſelues vnto you. I meane the greate Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion and Vſurie that reigneth frely in thys realme, and ſeme to be authoriſed by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wythin theſe .iii. yeres laſte paſte.</p>
            <p>☞ The Cleargie of the Citie of London, haue for theyr parte optayned by Parliament, authoritie to ouer te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thes euen after the exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of the landlordes and leaſemongers, and maye by the vertue of the acte requir for double ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, double tenthes. If the rent of any kynde of houſyng or grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de wythin the Citie of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don be raiſed (as ther is in dede veri much) fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> x.s, to xx.s: than may the perſone (whoe had be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore but xvi.d. ob.) by the vertu of this act, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde .ii.s .ix.d, the double. Byſydes this, the exactions that they take of the pore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons, is to much beyonde al reaſon and conſcience. No couple ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be maried, but theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt haue a dutie, as the call it. No woman may be purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but they and theyr ydle miniſters muſt haue ſome duties of hir. None ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be buried but they wyll haue a flieſe. Not three monethes before the beginning of this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: I had iuſt occaſion to be at the payme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this dutie for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buriyng of an honeſt pore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des were wylling to haue his body reuerendly laied in the ground, &amp; according to the cuſtome, gaue warninge to the curate that they woulde
<pb facs="tcp:25280:13"/> brynge the deade body to the churche: deſiryng him that he would do his dutie and to be there to receyue it, and accordyng to the cuſtome, to laye it in the grounde. But thys Rauen ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng the carion: coulde not but reueile it to the other carion byrdes of the ſame church, and ſo woulde needes come all together in a flocke to fetche theyr praye, wyth croſſe and holy water as they were wonte to do, notwythſtandynge the Kynges Iniunctions and late viſitation. The frendes of the deade man refuſed al thys and required to haue no more but the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune coffen to put the body in, agreynge to paye to the keeper therof his accuſtomed dutie, and in lyke maner to the graue maker, and the foure poore men to cary the bodye, ſo that the whole charges had ben but .vii.d.</p>
            <p>☞ But when the corps was buried, wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out other croſſe or holy water ſtycke, Dirige, or Maſſe, with praiers of as ſmal deuotion, as any pore curate could ſay, yet muſt we needes paye .vii.d. more That is to ſaye .i.d. to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, whiche he called an heade peny, and .vi.d. to .ii. clerkes that we had no neede of.</p>
            <p>☞ Thys was done in Sepulchres pariſhe in the Citie of Lodon. And if it ſhall pleaſe any of this noble aſſemble to trye the truth of this: I wyl verifie it where ſo euer I ſhal be called, euen in the preſence of all the ydle miniſters of the ſame churche.</p>
            <p>☞ This haue I written (moſte worthy coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſailours) to gyue you an occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſet ſuch an ordre in thys and ſuche other thynges, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we may haue miniſters founde vppon the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thes that we paie yerli to the churches: other
<pb facs="tcp:25280:13"/> els that it maye be leaful for vs to do ſuch mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteries our ſelues, and not to be thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to feede a ſorte of carion crowes, whiche are neuer ſo mery as when we lament the loſſe of our frendes.</p>
            <p>☞ Thys muche haue I ſpoken of the extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that reygneth frely in the Clergie. Nowe, wyth your pacience, I wyl with like breuitie, ſpeake of the great &amp; intollerable vſurie, which at this daie, reigneth ſo frely this realme ouer al, and chiefely in the Citie of London: that it is taken for moſte leaful gaines. Yea it is wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte hereſie to reproue it, for men ſay it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by Parliament. Wel. The moſt part, I am ſure, of this moſt Godly aſſemble and par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: do knowe that the occaſion of the acte that paſſed here co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning Vſurie: was the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaciable deſire of the vſurers, who coulde not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with Vſurie, vnleſſe it were vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable much. To reſtrayne this gredy deſire of theirs therfore, it was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muned and agreed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and by the authoritie of Parliament, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed: that none ſhould take aboue .x.li. by yere for the lone of an .C.li.</p>
            <p>☞ Alas that euer any chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble ſhould be ſo voied of gods holy ſpirite, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould alowe for leaful: any thynge that Gods word forbiddeth, Be not abaſhed (moſt worthy coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaylours) to cal this acte into queſtion againe. Scan the wordes of the Pſalmiſt concerning this matter, Lorde, ſayth he, who ſhal enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy tabernacle, and who ſhal reſt in thy holy mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine? H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> anſwereth. That entreth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſpot &amp; worketh ryght. That ſpeaketh truth in his hert, &amp; hath not deceiued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his tonge, that
<pb facs="tcp:25280:14"/> hath done his neighbour ho harme, nor accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any reproche againſt his neighbour. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth not the wicked: but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feare the Lorde, he glorifieth &amp; praiſeth. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſwereth to his neighbour &amp; deceyueth hym not. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath not giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his money vnto vſurie, &amp; hath not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken gyftes &amp; rewardes agaynſt the innocent.</p>
            <p>☞ If you (moſte chriſtian counſaylours) do glorie in the knowledge of Gods ſpirite, who hath ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe wordes by the prophet: howe can you ſuffre this acte to ſtande which ſhalbe a witnes againſt you in the later day, that you alowe that, which Goddes ſpirite forbiddeth?</p>
            <p>☞ If he that geueth not his money to Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: ſhal dwell in the Lordes tabernacle: where ſhal he dwel that giueth his money to Vſury? ſhal he not be ſhutte out &amp; caſt into vtter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? Theyr workes be contrary, &amp; why ſhould not their rewarde be alſo contrary? If the one be receyued in: the other muſt be ſhut out. Yea and you that haue made this lawe, vnleſſe you do reuoke it and eſtablyſh an act to the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: the Brydegroume, the onely ſonne of God, ſhal at the laſte daye deny you and ſaye that he neuer knewe you,<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> Depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, ſhal he ſaye, al ye workers yf iniquitie. Scanne the wordes of the Prophete therfore, and ſcanne the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of oure ſauioure Chriſte alſo, in the .vi. of Luke, where he ſayeth thus. Do you lende lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge for no gaynes therof, and your rewarde ſhalbe plentuous, and you ſhalbe ſonnes of the higheſt, bicauſe he is gentle &amp; liberall, towarde the vnthankful and wicked.</p>
            <p>☞ I am not ignoraunte what Gloſſes haue ben made vpon this place, and howe men haue
<pb facs="tcp:25280:14"/> wreſted &amp; made it no precept, but a counſaile of our ſauiour, &amp; therfore not to infer neceſſitie to chriſtians but to leaue them at libertie either to do it or leaue it vndone.</p>
            <p>☞ Oh mercifull Lorde, what maner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is it that theſe men profeſſe?</p>
            <p>☞ They boaſt them ſelues to bee the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſte and ſetters forthe of his glorie.</p>
            <p>☞ They wyll beare the name of hym and be called chriſtians, and yet wylbe at libertie to choſe whether they luſte, to folowe hys coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle or leaue it vndone.</p>
            <p>☞ Our ſhepherd Chriſte, of whoſe flocke they boaſte them ſelues to bee, ſayeth that hys ſheepe heare his voyce and folowe hym.</p>
            <p>And immediatly before, he ſheweth,<note place="margin">Iohn. 10</note> the cauſe why the Iewes dyd not credyt hys wordes, to be none other: but that thei wer not his ſhepe.</p>
            <p>☞ And doubte ye not (moſte worthy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaylours) what ſo euer he is that wyll defende or teach, that any one lytle iote of the counſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of Chriſt ſhoulde be ſo vaynly ſpoken that any of hys flocke myght refuſe to practiſe the ſame in hys lyuynge to the vttermoſte of hys power: is noleſſe then a membre of the Deuell, and a verey Antichriſte.</p>
            <p>☞ For he that deſyreth not in hys herte to practiſe in his lyueynge, all the counſayles of Chriſte our maiſter and teachar: ſhall be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred amonge the obſtinate Iewes, for none of the flocke of Chriſt, becauſe he heareth not his voice nor foloweth him. Thus I mak an ende</p>
            <p>Wyſhyng vnto you (moſt worthy counſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſpirit that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> primitiue church gaue vnto the multitude of beleuers,<note place="margin">Actu. 4.</note> one herte
<pb facs="tcp:25280:15"/> one mynde, &amp; to eſteme nothyng of this worlde as theyr owne, miniſtrynge vnto euery one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to his neceſſities. That you led by the ſame ſpirite, may at the leſtwaye, ordeine ſuch a lawe that the oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the pore reigne not frely amonge them that beare the name of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, But if they wyll be ſtyll oppreſſyng the pore membres of Chriſt after once or twyſe ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: let them nomore be named chriſtians after Chriſt whom thei ſerue not, but Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtes after Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon whoſe badge they beare. And this reformacion had, no doubt the maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of God ſhal ſo appere in all your decres, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none ſo wicked a creature ſhalbe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſo bold as once to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his mouth againſt the ordre that you ſhal take in al matters of religion. Yea the very enimies of Dauid ſhall do Omage vnto Solomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his wiſdom. Al the Kynges chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtined ſhal learne at you to reforme theyr chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. You ſhalbe eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the light of al the world.</p>
            <p>☞ But if ye lette theſe thynges paſſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not: be ye ſure the Lorde ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d your, wiſdome. Inuent, Decre, Eſtabliſh and authoriſe what you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: al ſhal come to nought. The wayes that you ſhall inuent to eſtablyſhe vnitie and concord: ſhalbe the occacions of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde. The thynges wherby you ſhal thinke to wyn prayſe through al the worlde: ſhal tourne to your vtter ſhame, and the wayes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ſhall inuent to eſtablyſh a kyngdome: ſhalbe the vtter ſubuercio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame. The mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifull father of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, indue you wyth hys ſpirit, that you be not part<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>takers of theſe plages.</p>
            <closer>AMEN</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25280:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25280:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25280:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
